Boris Artzybasheff Papers
Boris Artzybasheff Papers
1893-1966
Artzybasheff, Boris, 1899-1965
4.5 linear ft.
Spanning 1893 to 1966, the Boris Artzybasheff Papers comprises biographical material, correspondence, artwork, writings, and memorabilia of the Russian-American artist (1899-1965), who is perhaps most widely known for the more than 200 covers of Time magazine he produced between 1941 and 1965. Illuminating Artzybasheff's unique and versatile artistic style as well as his life as an immigrant in the United States, the collection documents the career of the illustrator, painter, designer, and author.
149479
Scope and Contents of the Collection
Arranged chronologically, the Correspondence (Box 1) consists of incoming and outgoing letters in Russian and French as well as English. Letters bearing the dates 1918 through 1923 are largely in Russian, most likely to and from Artzybasheff's mother, who was residing in Constantinople at the time. Correspondents during the remaining years (1934-1965) include literary figures (Edward H. Dodd; Charles G. Finney; William McCleery), advertising agencies (Daniel and Charles, Inc.; Shaller-Rubin Company, Inc.), and Time magazine. A selected index to the Correspondence follows the box list.
Artwork (Boxes 1-3) encompasses original book illustrations, two paintings, reproductions, research material, signatures, and sketches. Reproductions, which account for the bulk of the collection, are categorized by both format and subject. Personal greeting cards, book and magazine illustrations, and three-dimensional figures constitute Reproductions (by format). Book illustrations are arranged by book title when known. While magazine illustrations (mostly cover art) list each periodical title in the collection in which Artzybasheff's artwork appears, many of these items are cross-referenced to the subject Technology. Reproductions (by subject) categorizes images as Portraits, Technology, War images, and Miscellany. Images are identified by the name of the portrait subject, the client for which Artzybasheff produced advertising, the title of the periodical in which his work was displayed, or the title of the image as provided by Artzybasheff. Oversize Package #1 houses a variety of artwork, specifically, original book illustrations, a painting on wood, and large-format reproductions.
Writings (Box 4) consists of autobiographical reminiscences, three essays, two journals describing Artzybasheff's painting technique (including Time magazine portraits), one journal in Russian, and a published speech.
Memorabilia (Boxes 4-5) includes artwork by others, awards, calendars, personal documents, a price list of drawings, photographs of Artzybasheff and others, printed material, and miscellaneous typefaces. Printed material contains articles about Artzybasheff (1928-1954), newspaper clippings (1920-1965), a Russian newspaper (1937), several exhibition catalogs and announcements (1931-1966), book and artwork reviews (1922-1956), and documentation of Time magazine's 40th anniversary, which includes photographs of Artzybasheff. A genealogical record of the Southard family belonging to Artzybasheff's wife, Elisabeth Southard Snyder, and five periodicals are stored in Oversize Package #1.
Subject and Genre Headings
Art -- Painters; Art -- Illustrators; Artzybasheff, Boris, 1899-1965.; American wit and humor, Pictorial.; Commercial art.; Commercial artists -- United States.; Engravers -- United States.; Illustration of books -- United States -- 20th century.; Illustrators -- United States.; Machinery in art.; Magazine covers.; Magazine illustration -- 20th century.; Painters -- United States.; Painting -- Technique.; Painting, American.; Portrait painters.; Portrait painting -- 20th century.; Russian Americans.; Technology in art.; Time.; Articles.; Book illustrations.; Calendars (documents); Clippings (information artifacts); Correspondence.; Exhibition catalogs.; Notebooks.; Periodical illustrations.; Photographs.; Reminiscences.; Reproductions.; Artists.; Engravers.; Illustrators.; Painters.
Access Restrictions
The majority of our archival and manuscript collections are housed offsite and require advanced notice for retrieval. Researchers are encouraged to contact us in advance concerning the collection material they wish to access for their research.
Inventory
- Biographical material
  - Biographical material (Box 1)
- Correspondence
  - Correspondence, 1918-1965; undated; 2 folders (Box 1)
    See also Selected Index to Correspondence
- Artwork
  - Illustrations (book) (original)
    - Nansen (Oversize 1)
    - Untitled (Oversize 2)
  - Paintings
    - "NM illustrators' White & Cool Black" (Box 1)
    - "Scarlet Lake & BP", 16 Jun 1963; painting on wood (Oversize 1)
  - Reproductions
    - Greeting cards, personal, 1946-1954; undated (Oversize 3)
    - Illustrations, books
      - The adventures of Hajji Baba of Ispahan, 1935 (Box 1)
      - Nansen (Box 1)
      - Nansen (Oversize 1)
      - Various, by title, A-Z (Oversize 3)
      - Untitled (Oversize 1)
        Includes illustrations for "Midsummer Night's Dream," "The Night Before," and "Origin of the Flying Saucers"
    - Illustrations, magazine
      See also Reproductions by subject, below, for other examples of cover art.
      - American Artist cover art (Oversize 2)
      - Colophon cover art (Box 1)
      - Fortune cover art, Apr. 1941 (Oversize 3)
        See also Artwork Reproductions (by subject): Technology: Union Carbide & Carbon Corp.
      - Life articles, 1947; undated (Oversize 3)
      - Medical Economics, Jan 1953 (Box 1)
      - New Hope cover art (photocopy), Sep 1933 (Box 1)
      - Time cover art, 1941-1953 (Box 1)
      - Time cover art, "Farmer Warren North", 1959 (Box 1)
      - Time cover art, undated (Oversize 2)
      - Time cover art [?], undated; photographs (Box 1)
    - Three-dimensional figures, photographs of, undated (Box 1)
  - Reproductions by subject
    - Portraits
      - Burr, Harold Saxton, The Yale Journal of Biology & Medicine cover, Dec 1957 (Box 1)
      - Caribbean faces, 1948-1949; undated; advertising from Alcoa Steamship Company, Inc. (Oversize 4)
        See also Artwork Research Material: West Indies.
      - Caribbean faces, larger format items, advertising from Alcoa Steamship Company, Inc. (Oversize 1)
      - Dalton, Dorothy, 1921 (Box 1)
      - Doenitz, Karl, Der Spiegel cover, 1961 (Box 1)
      - Freud, Sigmund, Columbia Library Columns cover (Box 1)
      - Jones, Jesse H. (Oversize 4)
      - Smith, Howard K. (Oversize 4)
        See also Technology: CBS News, "Election Night, 1960" (Howard K. Smith), below.
    - Technology
      - Alcoa (Aluminum Company of America) advertising, includes photographs (Oversize 4)
      - American Airlines advertising (Box 1)
      - Atlas Copco advertising (Box 1)
      - Atlas Copco advertising, larger format (Oversize 1)
      - Avco advertising, 2 folders (Oversize 2)
      - Avco advertising (Oversize 3)
      - CBS News, "Election Night, 1960" (Howard K. Smith) (Oversize 3)
      - Conway Associates International, Inc. advertising (Box 1)
      - Dateline cover art (Box 1)
      - Dun's Review and Modern Industry cover art, June 1959 (Box 1)
      - "Executive of the Future", 1952; 1956,; 1961,; 1966 (Oversize 3)
        Cover art from Esquire, Apr. 1952; Overflow Mar. 1956; Museum of Science and Industry (Chicago) program announcement, 1961; Senior Science, Sept. 1966
      - Haloid Xerox Inc. advertising (Oversize 3)
      - "Improved Design for Modern Man", 1950 (Box 1)
      - "Jimmy Doolittle's 'Flying Engine' ", Esquire cover art, 5 Sep 1932 (Box 1)
      - Machine Design cover art, 10 May 1962 (Box 1)
      - Nation's Business cover art, Mar 1951; Jun 1953 (Oversize 3)
      - "New Quick-think Lawyer", 1954 (Box 1)
      - "New Quick-think Lawyer", 1954 (Oversize 1)
      - Production cover art, Sep 1960 (Box 1)
      - Railway Express Agency, Inc. advertising (Box 1)
      - St. Paul Insurance Companies advertising, 1965 (Box 1)
      - Shell X-100 Motor Oil advertising (Oversize 1)
      - [John] Sutherland Prod's Inc., includes storyboards for television commercial (Oversize 2)
      - Time subscription advertising (Box 1)
      - "The Twentieth Century Physician" (Box 1)
      - Union Carbide & Carbon Corp., Fortune cover art (Oversize 4)
      - Wickwire Spencer Steel Corp. (Box 1)
      - Wickwire Spencer Steel Corp. (Oversize 2)
      - Miscellany (Oversize 4)
    - War images
      - Hartford (Conn.) advertising for scrap metal drive (Box 1)
      - Vultee Aircraft, Inc. advertising (Oversize 3)
      - Wickwire Spencer Steel Corp. "Ain't going to study war no more..." (Oversize 2)
      - Miscellany (Box 1)
      - Miscellany (Oversize 2)
    - Miscellany
      - "Anxiety, Frustration, Repressed Hostility" (Oversize 2)
      - "Art Director, as seen by Artzybasheff" (Oversize 3)
      - Ex Libris Studio advertising, 1919 (Box 2)
      - "A Flag for the United Nations", 1945 (Box 2)
      - Frankfort Distillers Corp. advertising for Paul Jones (Oversize 1)
      - [Chas. M.] Higgins & Co., Inc. advertising for Higgins' American Drawing Inks (Box 2)
      - "Indecision, Timidity, Infantilism" (Oversize 2)
      - Logan Drinking Cup Co. advertising for Ajax and Aero Sanitary Drinking Cups (Box 2)
      - "Man Coddling His Ulcers" (Box 2)
      - "Naught so sweet as Melancholy", 1954 (Box 2)
      - Pan American World Airways advertising (Oversize 2)
      - Pan American World Airways advertising, poster
      - Parker Pen Company advertising, 1947; undated (Oversize 3)
      - The Russian Eagle menu (Box 2)
      - The Russian Inn menu (Box 2)
      - Time advertising, 1950; 1952,; undated (Oversize 4)
        See also Technology: Time subscription advertising, above.
      - "We Are Getting to the Bottom of It", 1948 (Oversize 3)
      - Wisconsin (State) advertising (Box 2)
      - Worthy Paper Company advertising (Box 2)
      - Miscellaneous images (Box 2)
      - Miscellaneous images (Oversize 1)
  - Research material (West Indies), undated; photographs, Alcoa Steamship Company, Inc. advertising; 3 folders (Box 2)
  - Signatures (Box 2)
  - Sketches (original), pencil (Box 2)
  - Sketches (original), pencil and watercolor, includes research material (Box 2)
- Writings
  - Autobiographical, holograph, typescript notes, reminiscences; 2 folders (Box 2)
  - Essays
    - "The Fan Mail of Boris Artzybasheff", Jul 1937; Published in Esquire (Box 3)
    - "The Magnificent Umpfs", holograph draft (Box 3)
    - "The Purgatory", typescript ms. drafts with holograph corrections (Box 3)
  - Journals, artwork, 1957-1965; 2 items (Box 3)
  - Journal, Russian, 1919 (Box 3)
  - Speech, "Let George Do It!", Dec. 5, 1940; Trade Book Clinic, New York,; published 1941 (Box 3)
- Memorabilia
  - Artwork by others
    - Originals, 1946; undated; caricature sketches (5), silhouette (1) (Box 3)
    - Reproductions, undated (Box 3)
  - Awards, 1954; 1961 (Box 3)
  - Calendars, 1955-1958 (Box 3)
  - Calendars, 1959-1965 (Oversize 4)
  - Financial material, price list of drawings, miscellany (Box 3)
  - Genealogical record, Southard family, belonging to wife, Elisabeth Southard Snyder (Oversize 2)
  - Photographs
    - Artzybasheff, Boris, undated; 3 folders (Box 3)
      See also Printed material: Time 40th anniversary
    - Family, friends, and landscapes, undated (Box 4)
  - Printed material
    - Articles about, 1928-1954; undated (Box 4)
    - Book, An illustrated introduction to psychoanalysis by Kenji Ohtsuki, gift from author, for use of Artzybasheff illustration, p. 191; in Japanese (Box 4)
    - Clippings, 1920-1965; undated; 2 folders (Box 4)
    - Clippings, Russian newspaper, 1937 (Box 4)
    - Exhibition catalogs, announcements, 1931-1966; undated (Box 4)
    - Periodical, Kaiser Aluminum News, 1966; 5 issues (Box 4)
    - Reviews, 1922-1939; 1956,; undated (Box 4)
    - Time 40th anniversary, 1963; including photographs (Box 4)
    - Time, "Famous Faces of Forty Years", 1963 (Oversize 3)
  - Typefaces (Oversize 3)
  - Miscellanea, 1893-1962; undated; certificates, personal documents, identification cards, passports, visas, miscellany (some in Russian) (Box 4)
  - Miscellanea, 1893-1962; undated; certificates, personal documents, identification cards, passports, visas, miscellany (some in Russian) (Oversize 4)
Selected index to correspondence
Daniel and Charles, Inc. 1965 Mar. 9 (outgoing typescript) 1965 Mar. 12
Dodd, Edward H. 1964 June 2
Finney, Charles G. 1935 July 7 1936 Sept. 8 (writings attached)
McCleery, William 1965 Jan. 5 1965 Jan. 15 (outgoing carbon) 1965 Feb. 8 1965 Mar. 17
National Historic Shrines Foundation, Inc. 1965 Feb. 17
Princeton University see McCleery, William
Shaller-Rubin Company, Inc. 1965 Apr. 15
Thompson, Ralph and Marcia 1956 Jan. 2 (outgoing holograph) 1958 Aug. (outgoing holograph) 1962 Mar. 12 (outgoing holograph) undated (2 outgoing holograph letters, 1 from wife Betty)
Time 1964 Sept. 15 1964 Sept. 21 1964 Sept. 28 1964 Oct. 30 1965 Feb. 4
United States. Department of State 1920 Nov. 13 (re: visa for mother)